大家好，我是TheCherno，欢迎回到我的OpenGL系列教程
hey, what's up guys, my name is TheCherno, welcome back to my OpenGL series
那么今天我们要讨论的是着色器中的统一变量
so today we're gonna be talking about uniforms in shaders
并且我特别想谈谈我们如何缓存统一变量
and specifically I wanted to talk about how we can cache uniforms
并且通常来说，我们可以用一种更聪明的方式来处理统一变量
and in general just how we can deal with uniforms in a bit of a smarter way
因为我们都知道怎么设置统一变量
because we all know how to kind of set uniforms
我已经制作了一个关于OpenGL统一变量和着色器之类的视频
I've got a video on uniforms in OpenGL and shaders and all that stuff
如果你们还没看过的话，可以去看看那个，但具体来说
check that out, if you haven't already, but specifically
而不是从GPU从OpenGL中检索统一变量
instead of just retrieving uniforms from OpenGL from our GPU
每次我们要设置统一变量的时候
every single time we need to set a uniform
实际上，我们可以做很多不同的事情来保留那个位置
there are many different things that we can actually do to kind of retain that location
并利用一旦统一变量被检索到的事实
and take advantage of the fact that once uniforms have kind of been retrieved
你们知道的，一旦我们编译了着色器
you know, once we've compiled our shader
我们就在我们的GPU上得到了那种实际的着色器对象
we've got that actual kind of shader object on our GPU
当然，GPU中的着色器知道所有的统一变量
and of course the shader in the GPU is aware of all of the uniforms
这些都包含在其中的所有有效的统一变量中
that are kind of contained within and all the valid uniforms
一旦我们得到了那个所有的数据
once we've got all that data
我们没有理由不断地查询GPU，就像
there's no reason for us to continually query the GPU being like
嘿，请告诉我，我的统一变量在哪里
hey, please tell me what like where my uniform is
因为我们应该已经知道那些了，你们应该知道，你们应该知道
because we should already know that stuff, and as you know, as you should know
几乎所有你们实际运行的OpenGL调用
pretty much any OpenGL call that you actually run
要比你们实际能做的C++风格的东西慢很多
is going to be slower than a lot of the C++ style stuff that you can actually do
因为有很多会访问GPU
because a lot of it actually hits the GPU
因此需要更多的处理能力
and thus kind of requires a little bit more processing power
这比我们做更简单的事情要花费更多的时间
and takes more time than if we did something a lot more simple
所以今天我们具体要讲的就是缓存统一变量
so, today's specifically we're going to talk about caching that uniform
这样我们就能在任何时候检索位置
so that we can just kind of retrieve the location at any time
我们想要建立一个小系统，一个非常简单的系统
we want basically building a little system, a very very simple system
它只是持有了给定名称的统一变量的位置
that just holds on to a uniform location for a given name that we have
在我们C++中的着色器对象里面
inside our kind of C++ shader object
但总的来说，我以后可能会再多讲一点
but in general, I may talk about this a little bit more in the future
因为通常的情况是
because what typically happens is
一旦你们真正在每种游戏引擎中经常编译你们的着色器
once you actually compile your shader pretty much every kind of game engine
或者每一种渲染引擎都会实际读取那个着色器的源代码
or every kind of rendering engine is actually going to physically read that shader source code
然后决定该怎么做，对吧
and then determine what to kind of do with that, right
所以换句话说，如果我们加载一个着色器
so in other words, if we just kind of load a shader
我们可以引导使用OpenGL来做所有这些事情
and we can pilot and we use OpenGL to do all that stuff
我们要做的另一件很有用的事是在C++中读取源代码的着色器
another very useful thing for us to do is actually kind of read the shader of source code inside C++
然后从中提取数据，这样你们就能找到所有的属性
and then extract data from it, so from that you can actually find out all the attributes
所有的统一变量，所有的功能，所有在着色器里的东西
all of the uniforms, all of the functions, everything that is in the shader
我们可以写一个程序本质上读取文本和着色器源代码
we can write a program essentially that just kind of reads that text that shader source code
然后从那里，它可以智能地几乎
and then from there, it can intelligently almost
将其转换为我们可以在运行时利用和使用的实际数据
convert it into actual data that we can leverage and use at runtime
在这样的设置中你们有一个合适的系统，一个合适的引擎
and so in a setup like that where you've got a proper system, and a proper engine like that
你们通常只会读取你们的着色器源代码
you would typically just read your shader source code
然后在实际的着色器文本中找到所有的统一变量
and then find all of the uniforms in the actual shader text
然后检索所有的位置或者确认所有的统一变量
and then retrieve all the locations or validate all of the uniforms
基本上当你们编译你们的着色器时，在这种情况下，当你得到
basically when you're compiling your shader, so in that case anytime you get
你们知道，当你们的渲染器在你们的着色器中设置统一变量
you know, when your renderer is actually setting uniforms in your shader
所有那些都已经完成了
all of that stuff has already been done
你们已经有了所有的位置，你们可以很容易地检查统一变量是否存在
you already have all the locations, you can easily check to see if a uniform even exists or not
而不涉及OpenGL，为什么，因为你们已经读取到了着色器源代码
without touching OpenGL, why, because you've read the shader source code
所以那是在一个更完整的系统中会出现的情况
so that is something that would happen in a more complete system
今天我要给大家展示的是一种快速而肮脏的小技巧
what I'm showing you guys today is a quick and dirty little kind of hack
如果你们想让你们的程序快一点
if you will just to speed up your program a little bit
如果你们只是建立一些快速的OpenGL
if you're just building something quick and OpenGL
你们不希望有这么庞大的渲染引擎之类的设置
you don't want to have this massive, like rendering engine or anything like that set up
你们只是想快速地加快你们的代码而不需要花太多的精力
and you just want to kind of speed up your code quickly without much effort really
通过使用一个简单的方法来快速设置统一变量
by just kind of you know someone's like one simple trick to faster uniform setting
就是那样的，对吧，事实上
that's kind of what this is, right, in fact
如果我说出视频的名字，我可能就会惹上你们所有人的麻烦
if I name the video that I'll probably just get in trouble with all of you guys
所以我可能不会说这是一个简单的技巧来加速你们的统一变量
so I might not name it one simple trick to speed up your uniform
也许我会，我们等着瞧，但重点是它超级简单
maybe I will we'll see, but the point is it's super simple
这是一种很容易就能加快统一变量设置的方法
and it's a way that we can just easily speed up our uniform setting
但不是每次从OpenGL检索位置，而是通过缓存它，让我们看一下
but just not retrieving the location every time from OpenGL, but by caching it, let's take a look
那么我有这个非常非常简单的着色器类
so I have this very very simple shader class that we have here
这是OpenGL系列的剩余部分，它真正拥有的是
kind of leftover from the OpenGL series and what it has really is
它代表的是一个包含RendererID的着色器
and what it represents is just basically a shader which contains you know a RendererID
所以它有点像编译过的着色器对象
so it's kind of like a compiled shader object
这就像一个实际编译的CPU表示
this is like the CPU representation of an actual compiled
在我们的GPU上创建着色器对象，一些绑定和解绑的函数
and created shader object on our GPU, a bunch of functions for like binding and unbinding it
同时还要设置所有的统一变量，所以这是最重要的
and also setting all of these uniforms, so this is kind of the meat of everything
如果我们看一下这段代码实际上做了什么，它真的非常非常简单
and if we take a look at what that code actually does, it's really really simple
它所做的就是对于我们设定的每个统一变量
all it really does is for every uniform that we set here
比如说这里有一个三个分量的向量，也就是vec3
such as let's just say a three component vector here, vec3
它从OpenGL获取位置
it gets the location from the from OpenGL
对吧，使用我们的RenderID和统一变量的名称
right, using our RenderID and the name of the uniform
然后它设置那个统一变量，我的意思是，我们有这个GLCall宏
and then it sets that uniform, right, now I mean, we've got this GLCall macro
顺便说一下，这是相当古老的，不是你们现在通常会使用的东西
by the way, which is quite old and not something you would typically use nowadays
但是你们知道的，正如你们所见
but and you know you can see
这个位置的东西没有包装在宏中，但那不是重点
this location stuff isn't wrapped in that macro, but that's besides the point
如果我们想让它更具可读性，这才是我的重点
if we were to just make this even more readable, it's kind of my point of that
这有点像我们最后得到的非常非常简单，对吧
then this is kind of like what we end up with really really simple right
我们会检索位置，如果我们想设置统一变量，我们会在这里获得位置
we basically retrieve the location, if we want to set the uniform, we get the location here
就是个整数，然后我们在这里用它
which is going to be an integer, and then we use that here
你们甚至可以使用某种验证来确保它确实存在，因为我们知道
and you could even use some kind of validation to make sure that that actually exists, because we know that
如果它是-1，对吧，那么它是无效的，我们可以这样做
if it is -1, right, then it's invalid, so what we might do is something like this
这是OpenGL中很常见的代码，对吧
this is a very very common code that you see in OpenGL quite often, right
也就是一些人基本上检索位置
where someone basically retrieves the location
检查位置是否为-1，然后设置统一变量，就是那样，完成了
checks to see if the location is like -1 or not, and then sets the uniform, and that's it, that's done
那将非常有效，但问题是它的效率有点低
that's going to work beautifully, but the problem is it's a little bit inefficient
因为就像我提到的，这将是一段活跃代码，如果你们经常触发它
because again as I mentioned, this is going to be a piece of hot code that if you hit it often
你们会遇到麻烦的，我们甚至会
you're going to run into problems, and we could even
通过使用profiler来测试它
chit like test that out by just using the profiler here
我想如果我们像调试分析器那样
I think if we go like you know debug profiler performances flora
我们展示它，我们展示它，然后开始一个新的性能
we show that, we kind of show that and start like a new performance session
看看我们是否有这样一个项目，你们知道的，每个帧都有设置统一变量
and take a look if we had a program that was you know setting uniforms every frame
你们会说这是一段很活跃代码，对吧
you'd say that this would come up as kind of a hot piece of code, right
因为这个东西每次都会被触发，对吧
because this is something that's going to get hit often every time, right
因为这是一个GLCall，它需要一些时间，所以我们可以做的是
and since it is a GLCall, it takes a bit of time to do, so what we can do instead is
检索这个位置，就像你们看到的，对吧，把它存储在一个哈希映射中
grab this location as you can see we're doing, right, and then store it in just a hash map
所以如果我们跳到头文件，我们能做的就是包含一个unordered_map
so if we hop over to our header file, what we can do is just include an unordered_map
然后这里我们输入std::unordered_map
and then over here we'll just type in std::unordered_map
这里的键就是我们的名字
now a key here is going to be our actual name
所以说一个字符串代表我们想要检索的统一变量的名字
so a string which represents the name of our uniform that we want to kind of retrieve
然后GLint会是值类型，对吧，因为那实际上是OpenGL的类型
and then GLint is going to be the value, right, because that's actually the OpenGL
我确定了我们使用的特定的统一变量位置
I identify that we use for that particular uniform location
我们可以叫这个m_UniformLocationCache，好了
we can call this m_UniformLocationCache, right
然后这实际上是要做什么
and then what this is going to essentially do
我们会在每次我们想要检索位置时使用这个
and where we're actually going to use this is every time that we want to retrieve a location
我们将检查它是否存在于映射中
we'll check to see if it exists in the map
如果有，我们就不需要从OpenGL检索它了
and if it does, then no need for us to actually retrieve it from OpenGL
为了实现那个，我们要为自己做一个方便函数，叫GLint
to do that, we're going to make a little convenience function for ourself called GLint
我将把这个放在底部，也就是GLint GetUniformLocation
and I'm going to put this at the bottom here GLint GetUniformLocation
这将再次接受一个const std::string&，也就是我们实际的name
this is again going to take in a const string reference, which is going to be our actual name
并将返回一个GLint，对吧
and is going to return a GLint, right
但是这个函数的作用有点不同
but what this function is going to do is going to be a little bit different
那么我们现在有的，如果我在这里创建它
then what we currently have, if I just kind of create it here
它只会再次获得位置
what it's going to do is only get the location again
如果已经有了，就检查缓存
if it's already, checked the cache
第一步是检查缓存，看看我们是否有那个值在里面
the first step is to check the cache, and see if we've actually got that value in there
所以如果这个m_UniformLocationCache实际上包含
so if this m_UniformLocationCache actually contains
如果我们在这里使用find，name是键，如果这个已经存在
so if we use find here with the name is the key, if this actually already exists
如果缓存中有一个统一变量的名字，基本上我们可以这样做
if the cache contains a uniform with this name, so basically we can do that by just saying
如果不等于m_UniformLocationCache.end()，然后像那样简单返回
if it doesn't equal m_UniformLocationCache.end(), then we just return that simple as that
所以我们还是用m_UniformLocationCache[name]，就像这样
so we'll just do m_UniformLocationCache name like this again
这个只是将缓存返回给我们的数据结构中已经存在的值
what this does is just returns the cache to value that already exists inside our data structure
这意味着，我们的工作已经完成了，如果它不在缓存中
and that means that work, our work has done now, if it's not in the cache
然后我们需要做的是通过使用这里的代码来检索它，对吧
then what we need to do is retrieve it just by using this code here, right
然后把它存储在缓存里，我们可以这么做
then store it in the cache, which we can do
只要输入m_UniformLocationCache[name] = location，对吧
by just typing in m_UniformLocationCache name equals location, right
所以现在我们把它存储在缓存里，然后显然我们还需要返回它
so we're now storing it in the cache, and then obviously we still need to return it
因为这个函数检索的是统一位置，好了，就那么简单
because this function retrieves the uniform location, all right, simple as that
我可能要做的另一件事是将这个函数标记为const
one other thing I would do potentially is mark this function as const
成为那样的原因是，你们知道的，这就是它的本质
the reason it being that, you know, this is just kind of it's what it is
它应该只是检索一个统一变量的位置
it's supposed to be something that just retrieves a uniform location
它并没有修改我们的着色器或者做任何事情
it's not really modifying our shader or doing anything at all of that nature now
因为就像如果我们确实标记了const
since like if we do marked as const
你们会注意到我们会得到一个错误，我们会得到一个错误的原因是
you'll notice we will actually get an error, and the reason we'll get an error is because
我们实际上是在修改m_UniformLocationCache，就在那儿设置它的
we're actually modifying m_UniformLocationCache, we're setting it right over here
正如你们所看到的，那导致了这个区域的错误，就在这儿
and as you can see that results in an error in this area, right here
顺便说一下，它只是没有编译它
by the way, it's totally, it just hasn't compiled it
所以那完全没问题，但这确实是个错误
so that's totally fine, but this is actually a real error
如果我按control f7，你们就会看到那是行不通的
if I hit control f7, you'll see that that's not going to work
所以我们需要做的是，把m_UniformLocationCache标记为可变变量
so what we need to do is, basically mark our uniform location cache as a mutable variable
那意味着它可以被常量函数修改
what that means is that it can be modified by a const function
现在这个可能有点违反直觉
now this might be a little bit counterintuitive
为什么要创建不可变变量，比如为什么标记函数是常量
why are you creating immutable variable, like why markes function is constant
但是，我再次解释这个函数被标记为常量的原因是
but again, I'm explaining that the reason this function is marked as constant is
因为实际操作只是读取我们统一变量的位置，对吧
because the actual operation is just reading the location of our uniform, right
底层实现缓存这个值
the underlying implementation cache the value
但那对调用者来说并不重要，这并不是真正的修改
but that's not important to the caller basically, it's not really modifying
它根本没有修改我们的着色器
it's not really modifying our shader at all
它所做的只是将信息保存在缓存中，这完全没问题，好了
what it is doing is just keeping information inside a cache, which is totally fine, okay
现在我们得到了这个，而不是每次都做这些
so now that we've got this, instead of doing all of this stuff every time
以及手动获取我们统一变量的位置
and getting our location manually
我们现在可以用名字来调用这个GetUniformLocation
what we can just do now is call this GetUniformLocation with the name
就那样，那就是我们的位置
and that's it, that is what our location becomes
那么接下来会发生什么呢，我们一会儿会演示
so now what happens, and we'll demonstrate it in a minute
我只是快速地替换了所有这些
I just quickly replace all of these
现在，如果在这放一个断点，然后运行这个程序，会发生什么，好了
now what happens if I put a break point here and run this program, okay
那么现在我正在运行我的程序
so now that I'm running my program
你们就可以看到，我们试图将这个MVP矩阵统一设置为一个特定的值
you can see that we're trying to set this mvp matrix uniform to a certain value
它就会运行这个GetUniformLocation函数
what happens is it's going to of course run this GetUniformLocation function
这第一次运行的情况当然是空的
which the first time this runs the cases of course somewhat empty
我的意思是在这个缓存中，u_Color和u_Texture已经在那里了
I mean in this cache has actually got u_Color and u_Texture already in there
但它没有，你们可以看到，它根本没有mvp的位置
but it doesn't as you can see, it doesn't have the mvp locations start at all
所以很明显它没有找到那个位置
so obviously it's not gonna find it
然后它就会从OpenGL获取那个位置
and then it's going to actually retrieve that location from OpenGL
将其存储在这个缓存中，然后返回该位置
store it inside the cache and then return that location
然后如果我按f5，我们就会到下一次
and then if I hit f5, and we come back to the next time
我们请求这个MVP矩阵的位置
we ask for this mvp matrix location
对吧，这个m_UniformLocationCache显然就会包含它
right, the m_UniformLocationCache  obviously contains it
这意味着现在它只是简单地返回这个统一变量的位置，正如你们看到的
which means that now it just simply returns this uniform location as you can see
并且那比实际查询OpenGL要快得多，就像
and that is a lot faster than actually querying OpenGL, and being like
嘿，这个统一变量的位置是什么
hey, what's this uniform location
好了，所以那就是所有的内容了
okay, so that's pretty much all there is to it
如果这能帮助你们，就在下面点个赞吧
if this helped you out, drop a like below
你们不能做的就是测试我们的代码，当然是在你们的代码库中测试
nothing you could do is test us out, of course in your code base
看看它有多快
see how much faster it is
运行一个快速的计时器，比较前后的性能
just run a quick, like, right, a quick timer that compares the performance before and after
并且然后你们可以在下面的评论区分享你们的结果
and then you can share your results in the comment section below
下次见，拜
I will see you next time, goodbye